Okay בוקר טוב. Boker Tov. Today's דף daf is כ״ה, chaf hey,
but we begin on the top of כ״ד עמוד ב׳, chaf daled
amud bet, and we actually are going to shift gears a bit.
We had an interesting
משנה mishnah about a brother that somebody marries two women בספק, b'safek,
and he had two brothers, and two people did it, and each
of them had two brothers. Anyway, the end of that משנה mishnah
ended that if they both of the brothers do ייבום, yibbum, they
shouldn't, one should do חליצה, chalitzah, one should do ייבום, yibbum, but
if they both do ייבום, yibbum, so יכנסו... yakansu...
the end of the משנה mishnah was
אם
קדמו וכנסו אין מוציאין מידם. im kadmu v'kansu ein motzin mi-yadam. If
they went ahead and they did it, and they both of them
did ייבום, yibbum, then they're allowed to stay married. So this משנה
mishnah now is going to sort of pick up a little bit
on that theme of marriages that are not supposed to happen, but
if they do, you allow them to remain. It's interesting that it
was interrupted with a משנה mishnah which in a way should have
been the very first משנה mishnah of the מסכת, masekhet, or at
least the גמרא Gemara should have been the first גמרא Gemara of
the מסכת masekhet that discussed the idea that the older son is
supposed to be the one that the primary obligation of ייבום yibbum
devolves around, falls on, and that led to the גמרא Gemara to
look at the פסוק pasuk about the מצווה mitzvah of ייבום yibbum
and we erased it anyway about והיה הבכור אשר תלד v'hayah habechor
asher teled and interpret, really get to the פסוקים pesukim and interpret
something about is it talking that the son is named after the
father, is it talking about that the person who does the ייבום
yibbum inherits his brother, which is how we interpret it. So got
to some core issues about understanding the פסוקים pesukim and who has
the obligation of ייבום yibbum and what happens as a result of
ייבום. yibbum. But that sort of in a way was a very
early discussion that somewhat interrupted things here because now we get back,
as I said, to picking up on the theme ended by one
משנה mishnah back about if a wedding happens that shouldn't have happened,
whether we allow it to remain that way or not. So with
that in mind, let's look at the משנה mishnah on כ״ד עמוד
ב׳, chaf daled amud bet, and we have the
following: הנישש על השפחה ונשתחררה. Ha-neeshash al hashifchah v'nishtachrerah. Somebody is suspected
about having an affair with a
non-Jewish slave, a non-Jewish slave who's owned by a Jew who's quasi-Jewish
status, and somebody's suspected of having an affair with her and she
is now freed from her master. It could have been his slave
also, which of course happens all the time, cases
about
taking the sexual abuse or taking advantage of the power imbalance and
so on. Anyway, but even if it was somebody else's slave and
she was freed, או על הנכרית ונתגיירה, o al ha-nachrit v'nitgayerah, or
an affair with a non-Jewish woman and then she converted, הרי זה
לא יכנוס. Harei zeh lo yikanes. So you should not go ahead
and marry this woman, even if presumably it's a rumor, it doesn't
necessarily mean it's true. But don't go ahead and marry this woman.
Why? Because by marrying this woman that there was a rumor that
you were having an affair with, you basically just reinforce the rumor,
"Ah you see it's
true, obviously she converted and then got married, so clearly clearly the
rumor was
true." Okay? ואם כנס, V'im kanas, and if you did go ahead
and marry her, then אין מוציאין מידו, ein motzin mi-yado, we do
not force them to get divorced. So that's one scenario. I might
go till the end for a second. הנישש על אשת איש והוציאוה,
Ha-neeshash al eishet ish v'hotzi'uh, if somebody was suspected about having an
affair with a married woman and then she was divorced from her
husband, actually הוציאוה hotzi'uh has a language of they removed her from
her husband, we'll get to that in the גמרא, Gemara, but for
now we'll just say she was divorced from her husband מתחת ידו
mi-tachat yado from her husband אף על פי שכנס יוציא, Af al
pi she-kanas yotzi, even if בדיעבד bedi'avad if he married this woman
he has to go ahead and divorce her. Why? Because there we
are much more concerned that if you reinforce the belief, rumor, that
they actually were having an affair,
then maybe you start suspecting that the kids she had with her
first husband are ממזרים, mamzerim, or maybe just in general that's so
much worse because that's a because because in that case there is,
of course if that were the concern and we'll talk about that
in the גמרא, Gemara, I'm a little bit jumping ahead, that what
you would think about the kids she had with her first husband,
then by making her forcing her to divorce the second guy in
a way it doubly reinforces the rumor, right? It's one thing if
he marries her. If you go ahead and force him to divorce
her after he married her, then "Ah you see they really were
having an affair, that's why the Rabbis wouldn't let them stay married."
So the other problem though here is and the reason we might
be more מחמיר machmir בדיעבד bedi'avad is because in the other cases
it's just an idea of spreading a rumor or reinforcing a rumor.
But in this case
you actually were, the person, in addition to having done an עבירה,
aveirah, the result is that if a woman has an affair with
a man, a married woman has an affair with a man, she
becomes forbidden not only to her husband and to the man that
she had an affair with. So the. Therefore, in the other two
cases where he was, even if it were true that he was
sleeping with this non-Jewish woman or with this slave, he would not
become forbidden to them. There's no הלכה halacha that makes them forbidden
to him. So in those cases, it's just the concern of the
rumor, so בדיעבד bediavad we let it stand, where in this case,
there's a concern if the rumor really was true, then he would
not be allowed, you know, biblically to stay to marry this woman
he had an affair with. Of course, the remaining question is but
maybe the rumor isn't true? So why should we force a divorce?
Maybe it's a false rumor? You know? So we will take a
look at that in the גמרא, Gemara, but the basic difference in
the second case is that it's not just the rumor, were the
rumor to be true, he would not be allowed, you know, biblically
to be married to this woman.
Yes, Michael, what's your question? It clearly is just these specific two
cases, שפחה ונכרית, shifcha venochrit, but if it's rumors, then we can
just say, all right, well, if anyone's rumored to be sleeping with
anybody, we shouldn't allow them to get married. Oh, they were sleeping
around before they got married.
Well, yeah, but the point is is that the, I mean, so
in a little way תוספות Tosafot asks the question. I mean, so
your question is what about if it's an issue of פנויה? pnuya?
So if you take a look at תוספות, Tosafot, he says,
where's the תוספות? Tosafot?
If you take, well, you know what? We'll read the line in
the גמרא Gemara and then we'll read the תוספות. Tosafot. So the
גמרא Gemara says like this: האי גיורת מה תהא בה? hai giyoret
mah tehei bah? It sounds like fine, don't marry her, but it's
a good conversion. A woman who converted after maybe having had an
affair with a Jewish man and maybe for the purpose of marrying
this Jewish man, it says you shouldn't get married because it'll reinforce
the rumor, but it's but at least it sounds like the rumor,
like the marriage, like the conversion is still binding. So the גמרא
Gemara says: רמינהי, ramini, I'll ask you on this: אחד איש שנתגייר
לשום אשה, echad ish shenitgayer leshum isha, a man who converted for
the sake of getting married to a woman, ואחד אשה שנתגיירה לשום
איש, ve'echad isha shenitgayerah leshum ish, or a woman who converted for
the sake of marrying a man, וכן מי שנתגייר לשום שלחן מלכים,
vechen mi shenitgayer leshum shulchan melachim, or somebody who converted to being
Jewish for the sake of literally the table of kings, but basically
it means for the sake of the Jews had it really good.
Imagine that? Somebody converting to be Jewish because it was better economically
and socially to be Jewish than not Jewish. Okay, so we'll have
to wonder about when that was. לשום עבדי שלמה, leshum avdei Shlomo,
right. All right. So here's the time. In the time of דוד
ושלמה, David u'Shlomo, wanted to marry one of the servants of שלמה,
Shlomo, although beforehand like the servants of שלמה Shlomo weren't Jewish. Anyway,
אינם גרים דברי רבי נחמיה. einam gerim divrei Rabbi Nechemia. רבי נחמיה
Rabbi Nechemia says בדיעבד, bediavad, if you do it for ulterior motive,
it's not a good, you're not a good convert. שהיה רבי נחמיה
אומר, shehaya Rabbi Nechemia omer, because רבי נחמיה Rabbi Nechemia used to
say: אחד גירי אריות, echad girei arayot, whether if somebody converted because
the lions scared them into it, and אחד, ve'echad, sort of evoking
the whole story about the Samaritans in the in תנ"ך Tanach at
the end of בית ראשון. Bayit Rishon. ואחד גירי חלומות, ve'echad girei
chalomot,
or because of a dream, maybe because you had a dream that
scared you, or the way רש"י Rashi says it is that people
that have visions told you that you had to that you had
to convert. So you were doing it again because you were afraid
of some consequences of not converting, but not because of real religious
motivation. ואחד גירי מרדכי ואסתר, ve'echad girei Mordechai ve'Esther, or ורבים מעמי
הארץ מתיהדים כי נפל פחד היהודים עליהם. verabbim me'ammei ha'aretz mityahadim ki
nafal pachad ha'yehudim aleihem. That's a perfect example of converting because you're
afraid and for ulterior motive. You could have also mentioned those that
converted in the time of the חשמונאים Chashmonaim once we're dealing with
historical reasons why people converted not because of of proper religious motive.
So anyway, all those interestingly are out of fear. Anyway, אינם גרים,
einam gerim, none of them are true גרים gerim עד שיתגיירו בזמן
הזה ad sheyitgayeru bazman hazeh until they convert nowadays. הגמרא Hagemara says:
בזמן הזה סלקא דעתך? bazman hazeh salka datach? What's so important about
converting nowadays? אלא אימא כי בזמן הזה, ela eima ki bazman hazeh,
like things are nowadays where the Jews don't have it too good
and don't have it too bad, so they're not converting because they
think it'll be better to be Jewish, or they're not converting because
they're afraid of some consequences. They're converting out of true religious motivation.
So that's what רבי נחמיה Rabbi Nechemia says. Our משנה mishna suggests
not that way, that she's a full convert. The only question is
getting married. So הגמרא Hagemara says: הא איתמר עלה, ha itmar alah,
so how could that be? Because right now we only have the
voice of רבי נחמיה. Rabbi Nechemia. So הגמרא Hagemara says it was
said about it, הא איתמר עלה, ha itmar alah, אמר רב יצחק
בר שמואל בר מרתא משמיה דרב: amar Rav Yitzchak bar Shmuel bar
Marta mishmei deRav: הלכה כדברי האומר כולם גרים הם. halacha kedivrei ha'omer
kulam gerim heim. No, we don't rule like רבי נחמיה, Rabbi Nechemia,
we rule like the one who says they're all גרים, gerim, which
is quite fascinating, right? We haven't even quoted a different תנא. tanna.
We've just sort of asserted the presence of a different voice, כולם
גרים, kulam gerim, and we've פסק-ed pasken that way. Okay, which is
which is itself quite fascinating.
Now כולם גרים, kulam gerim, yeah, okay, כולם גרים הם.
kulam gerim heim. So הגמרא Hagemara now says, I'll get back to
this in a minute, but בדיעבד bediavad yes, she is a good
גיורת. giyoret. So הגמרא Hagemara says: אי הכי לכתחילה נמי? ei hachi
lechat'chila nami? So then why shouldn't you get married to this woman
who converted? So הגמרא Hagemara apparently initially thought that maybe the conversion
was suspect, and maybe the reason not to get married if a
woman converted after there was a rumor that she was having an
affair with a Jewish man was because maybe it wasn't a full
conversion, and that's why not to get married. But now that you're
saying it's a full conversion, why not get married? Of course, that
logic wouldn't have worked in the case of a slave, because if
you free a slave, you free a slave. There's no quasi, you
know, it's not like their motivation... It's completely irrelevant. It's the reality
of once she's free she becomes Jewish. So the גמרא Gemara says
if she's fully Jewish now that she converted and the slave is
fully free and therefore a fully Jewish woman, why should this man
not marry her? So the גמרא Gemara says לכתחילה נמי? l'chat'chila nami?
So משום דרב אשי mishum d'Rav Ashi because of what רב אשי
Rav Ashi says, דאמר רב אשי, d'amar Rav Ashi, הסר ממך עקשות
פה, haser mimcha ikshus peh, remove from yourself the perversion of the
mouth, ולזות שפתים, v'lazus sefasayim, and the sort of the rumor of
the lips, meaning try don't you know avoid having you know bad
rumors and bad things being said about you. So therefore you should
not reinforce all these rumors and therefore don't marry this woman that
you were having that you were suspect of having an affair with.
Okay, the question of course always is that well, if he really
was having an affair then he probably really would want to marry
her and how much is he going to be bothered you know
by reinforcing the rumor? But חז"ל Chazal are really saying that it's
not just your own personal concern about what people say, you know,
there's also a societal importance of not sort of it becoming acceptable,
you know, "Oh, people go ahead and have affairs and then they
get married" or whatever. So it raises interesting questions that try to
control a certain type of a discourse within the society, whatever the
actual facts might be, if things get sort of you know reinforced
these behaviors and talked about and so on, it just encourages you
know more behavior along those ways. But בדיעבד B'diavad actually they are
allowed to stay married. Now I want to deal with two points
quickly in the תוספות. Tosafot. תוספות Tosafot first of all asks Michael's
question, משום דרב אשי mishum d'Rav Ashi and הסר ממך עקשות פה.
haser mimcha ikshus peh. אומר ר"י Omer Ri דבניתן על הפנויה d'b'nitan
al hapanuya אין להחמיר ולקנוס ein l'hachmir u'liknos משום לזות שפתים. mishum
lazus sefasayim. How about if somebody is rumored to just you know
two single people to be sleeping together? Maybe they shouldn't get married
because it reinforces the rumor. He says no, דאדרבה מצוה לכונסה d'adaraba
mitzvah l'chonsah דבאנוסה כתיב d'ba'anusa kesiv ולו תהיה לאשה. v'lo siyeh l'ishah.
You had a funny quote אנוסה anusa again and not מפותה mefuta
but he says no, what you're supposed to do in that case
is to go ahead and then so nobody approves of the bad
behavior but then the proper thing is to get married. Whereas if
somebody is having an affair with a non-Jewish woman or with a
slave or whatever the proper thing is to break it off, you
know, whereas here the proper thing is to get married. So therefore
getting married as a result actually of course you know the question
is still open, okay but it still reinforces the rumor that it
actually happened. All right, it's an interesting question. But the behavior we'd
like to see in that case is them to get married. So
that's that issue. Now the issue about גירות Geirus I need to
say that this is an extremely central גמרא Gemara relating to issues
about גירות Geirus because the question is, there are two questions about
גירות. Geirus. One well, there's a lot of questions. But the two
big questions nowadays are, number one, what constitutes sufficient sense of you
know commitment, קבלת מצוות? Kabalas Mitzvos? How what is the definition of
that requirement? And the other is the question about motivation because and
often those are intertwined. If somebody is only converting for the sake
of marriage, how much are they really committed to become Jewish and
so on? This גמרא Gemara does not at all deal with the
depths of commitment. You could say that the concern about converting for
a wrong purpose that רבי נחמיה Rebbi Nechemia expresses is because if
you're converting for a wrong purpose you won't really be committing to
to to observe. But there's no hint of that in what רבי
נחמיה Rebbi Nechemia says. And it sounds like what רבי נחמיה Rebbi
Nechemia is saying is that ulterior motives is itself invalidates the process.
For it to be a legitimate process it has to be motivated
religiously. We rule against רבי נחמיה. Rebbi Nechemia. We rule that בדיעבד
b'diavad not, that it can be having these other at least בדיעבד
b'diavad it can have these other motivations. Then it becomes a big
question because while that's בדיעבד, b'diavad, לכתחילה l'chat'chila you're not supposed to
convert for the sake of marriage. And you know, that's like what
all the הלכה halacha literature said, of course you know now conversions
for the sake of marriage happen all the time, all the time.
You know and even in you know and you know and sort
of like within the range of Orthodox con you know sort of
communities, especially after the people already intermarried and then they want to
be converted and so on. So there's a lot of interesting תשובות
tshuvos about how these concerns about conversion for the sake of marriage
are less serious concerns nowadays even at the לכתחילה l'chat'chila level. One
primary תשובה tshuva written by what's his name נו... nu...
why can't I think of the name...
the name is escaping me...
anyway a name will occur to me... anyway an early פוסק posek
anyway
about about 100 years
ago... no no no not in Israel... here in the states... no
in Europe and then this and then... all right I'll think of
the name. Anyway the תשובה tshuva basically said that look, in the
past when you weren't allowed to or you know society forget legally
whatever, you wouldn't be able to marry a you know non-Jew couldn't
marry a Jew unless one of them had converted. So then the
whole conversion was totally for in order to enable the marriage. It
says whereas nowadays you know people often are you know people can
totally marry across religion. There's nothing stopping people from marrying across religion.
So to convert is not to make it possible. possible to get
married, often to convert has to do with other reasons like because,
you know, your future spouse wants you to be Jewish. So it’s
not and or, you know, there’s some something else there than’s just
about removing, you know, the obstacle to getting married. And sometimes, you
know, you would have gotten married anyway, but, you know, the family
of your spouse says, "No, I can only be married to a
Jew" or this or that. Well, so if only then it is
an obstacle from the spouse's perspective. That’s true. But the basic argument,
but the argument being that often therefore the motivation has a little
bit more to do with the desire to identify Jewish and not
just to remove an obstacle, because there aren’t really obstacles nowadays. And
often you have cases where people are like already
married,
you know, an intermarried couple. They’re already married. So they’re already married
and then they want to go ahead and convert. It’s not in
order to become married; it’s in order to be more Jewish. So,
anyway, there’s a lot of interesting תשובות Teshuvot around that and in
general around like we live in a very בדיעבד bedi'eved reality right
now anyway. So it’s all very nice to say לכתחילה, lechatchila, but
basically you say, "Okay, I’m not going to convert you, לכתחילה lechatchila
not allowed to convert," then they’ll say, "Fine," then they go ahead
and get married without converting, right? And then is that the better?
Like, okay, so we’re already dealing in a בדיעבד bedi'eved reality, right?
The בדיעבד bedi'eved reality is either they’re going to get married without
the spouse converting or they’re going to convert for ulterior motives. Which
is the better בדיעבד? bedi'eved? So these are the types of like
חשבונות cheshbonot and a lot of this, you know, has radically changed
nowadays in practice about, you know, so much of the conversions that
happen are related to marriage issues. I will say that another interesting
related question becomes and this is so fascinating that some people raise,
"No, no, it’s not just a לכתחילה lechatchila problem, because when you
convert you have to accept all מצוות mitzvot and you can’t, and
even if you say... not here, that's not... we'll be a סוגיא
sugya later, okay? Here's just about motivation. You have to accept all
מצוות. mitzvot. Look, some of this is debated what exactly the parameters
of this is, but here's an argument: and even if you don't
exclude one rabbinic מצוה, mitzvah, it's not good, it's not considered קבלת
מצוות. kabbalat mitzvot. So here if somebody basically converts and when they’re
not supposed to get and they’re planning on getting married, then they’re
not accepting all the מצוות mitzvot because they’re planning on violating the
הלכה halacha of not getting married after you convert and having been
having an affair with, you know, with a Jewish person, so that
should make it a not good בדיעבד bedi'eved conversion because you’re planning
on violating this הלכה." halacha. Okay, that’s a pretty extreme position. But
basically this גמרא Gemara is a very central issue around the question
of the need for motivation, sincere motivation, which totally we פוסקן posken
that that’s a לכתחילה, lechatchila, not a בדיעבד bedi'eved against רבי נחמיה.
Rabbi Nechemia. Yes, Charlie.
Might that פוסק posek be the thing Rabbi David Tzvi Hoffman?
No. I don’t know why I can’t remember the name, but it’ll
come to me. Yeah.
You keep on saying "affair," this עובדת כוכבים ovedet kochavim or the
שפחה shifcha were not פנויות, penuyot, they were...
No, I don’t mean by affair that it was adultery, I just
mean they were having a sexual relationship. Okay. Alright, so now the
גמרא Gemara says like this. Okay.
So the גמרא Gemara says, okay. תנו רבנן, Tanu Rabbanan, אין מקבלים
גרים לימות המשיח. ein mekabelim gerim lemot HaMashiach. We won’t accept גרים
gerim in the time of משיח Mashiach because sure, that’s when everybody
will want to convert, you
know, no, you needed to have converted when it was a little
bit harder. כיוצא בו, Kayotzei bo, well, okay, right.
לא קיבלו גרים לא בימי דוד ולא בימי שלמה. lo kibelu gerim
lo bimei David velo bimei Shlomo. So here’s about the question about
when it was, you know, don’t accept גרים gerim because if they’re
doing it for ulterior motives because they want to have it good.
אמר אלעזר מאי קרא, Amar Elazar mai kra, what’s the
פסוק? pasuk? הן גור יגור אפס מאותי מי גר אתך עליך יפול.
Hen gor yagor efes me'oti mi gar itach alayich yipol. So הן
גור יגור hen gor yagor means to dwell but here’s being read:
if somebody, if a גר ger comes to
convert, גר יגור ger yagor comes to convert, אפס מאותי, efes me'oti,
it has to be without me, it has to be like without
all of the of the benefit, without all of the obvious reward.
And then, you know, מי גר אתך, mi gar itach, somebody who
converts with you when things are not good, עליך יפול, alayich yipol,
then will have a portion with you in the future. Okay, it
raises questions, you know, דוד. David. תוספות Tosafot raises, again this gets
to the issue of the
בדיעבד, bedi'eved, the... so תוספות, Tosafot, so לא בימי דוד ולא בימי
שלמה, lo bimei David velo bimei Shlomo, תוספות Tosafot says,
מאיטי הגיתי ובת פרעה דבימי שלמה לא קשיא. Me'itai haGitti uvat Paroh
debimei Shlomo lo kashya. How about we do know that people converted,
you know, in the time of שלמה, Shlomo, all the people שלמה
Shlomo married, etc.? דמידי הוא דאמר אלא משום שולחן מלכים והני לאו
צריכי. demidi hu de'amar ela mishum shulchan melachim vehani lav tzrichi. Alright,
because they anyway were rich, so it wasn’t really ulterior motives. אבל
קשיא דמייתי בערך גבי מעשה דגבעוני בימי דוד נתגיירו גרים על ישראל
קנ אלף, aval kashya demaiti ba-erach gabei ma'aseh deGivoni bimei David nitgayeru
gerim al Yisrael kon aleph, right? So whatever, 150,000 גרים. gerim. יש
לומר דמאליהן נתגיירו. yesh lomar de'me'aleihen nitgayeru. כדאשכחן במרדכי ואסתר, dashkachan b'Mordechai
v'Esther, ורבים מעמי הארץ מתייהדים. v'rabbim me'ammei ha'aretz mityahadim. ויש ספרים שכתוב
בהם v'yesh sefarim shekatuv bahem לא קיבלו גרים לא בימי דוד ולא
בימי שלמה, lo kibelu gerim lo bimei David v'lo bimei Shlomo, אלא
שנעשו גרים גרורים. ela shenasu gerim gerurim.
So what does this exactly mean, מאליהן? mei'aleihen? The Rambam says that
it was like a בית דין של הדיוטות Beit Din shel hedyotot
who was מקבל mekabbel them. Meaning, they weren't supposed to convert, but
some you know any בית דין Beit Din can convert somebody, and
בדיעבד bedi'avad it works. So the reality is, yes, לכתחילה lechatchilah you're
not supposed to, but as I was sort of talking about contemporary
reality, it happens all the time and we've sort of said that
now we're anyway living the בדיעבד bedi'avad reality, so it's one בדיעבד
bedi'avad over another, but historically there've been a lot of cases where
בדיעבד bedi'avad this is exactly what happened and then בדיעבד bedi'avad it
actually works. As we said, you had what was the story with
Mordechai and Esther or the story about the חשמונאים? Chashmonaim? David, you
had a question. Yeah.
Right, Mordechai and Esther.
Yes, so that's what the מדרש Midrash says, so you know בדיעבד
bedi'avad it might have worked. Okay, very quickly.
I'm gonna ask about בת פרעה.
Bat Pharaoh. Well, that's what תוספות Tosafot asked. Yeah, right, so yeah.
Then you asked about the ערב רב. Erev Rav. What do you
say about that? I mean, כיסא דמשה's keisei de'Moshe not a בית
דין של הדיוטות. Beit Din shel hedyotot.
All right, I don't know if they ever converted. They were there
was always people that were hangers-on. Okay, let's move on with Shlomo
Kluger, I knew the name would come to me. So רב שלמה
קלוגר, Rav Shlomo Kluger, he wrote one in an early תשובה teshuvah
about how now in America, now whatever, now's the reality that people
get married even without converting, the idea that you can't convert if
people are anyway living together and planning on getting married is a
very different type of a חשבון. cheshbon. Okay, הנטען על אשת
איש, hanit'an al eshet ish, somebody who's now suspected of having an
affair with a married woman, they even בדיעבד bedi'avad have to get
divorced because if it's true, then they're not allowed even דאורייתא de'oraita
to be married. The question is, how do you know it's true?
Maybe it's not true. So let's take a look. This becomes a
very important discussion about what type of evidence you need for adultery
to create this problem. So אמר רב, amar Rav, רב Rav says,
ובעדים, ub'edim, the only time that you would force a divorce if
they got married after there was this rumor of an affair of
adultery would be if there were witnesses that they actually, actually adultery
was committed. And then you know objectively that she's אסורה asurah to
the guy she had the affair with, and then you force them
to get divorced. But if it's a stage of rumor, then... What
if he killed the guy... There were עדים edim with התראה, hatra'ah,
whatever. So okay, fine. We're not dealing with we're not dealing that
there's a בית דין Beit Din that does דיני נפשות, dinei nefashot,
but there is witnesses enough that she did it, that therefore and
only then do you force it to get divorced. Otherwise, it's a
rumor. We're not going to force her to get divorced if she
marries the other guy. So the גמרא Gemara says, אמר רב ששת,
amar Rav Sheshet, רב ששת Rav Sheshet said, אמינא, amina, I I
said that דכי נים ושכיב רב אמרה לשמעתא, d'ki nayim v'shachiv Rav
amrah l'shma'ata, רב Rav must've been falling asleep when he said that.
Why? דתניא, detanya, we taught in a ברייתא, braita, הנטען על אשת
איש והוציאוה על ידו, hanit'an al eshet ish v'hotziuha al yado, somebody
who's suspected of having an affair with a married woman and she
was divorced as a result,
ונתגרשה, v'nitgarsha, and she was divorced from her first husband, and then
ונתגרשה מתחת ידו ע"י אחר, v'nitgarsha mitachat yado al yedei acher, and
then she married somebody else. So she was suspected of having an
affair with ראובן, Reuven, then she went ahead and she married שמעון,
Shimon, okay, then not his brother, okay, she married she married ברק,
Barak, okay. So she married a different guy, not the guy she
was suspected of having an affair with, and then she got divorced
from guy number two. Then אם כנס לא יוציא, im kanas lo
yotzi, then if ראובן Reuven marries her after that, he can stay
married to her. Now you understand why, because the fact that she
went and married after her divorce a completely different guy, you know,
will undermine any rumors that she was having an affair with ראובן.
Reuven. If she was having an affair with ראובן, Reuven, she would've
married ראובן. Reuven. So clearly, if she went ahead and married some
some other person, presumably she wasn't having an affair with ראובן. Reuven.
Okay, and by the time she gets around to getting divorced from
guy number two and marrying ראובן, Reuven, people have even forgotten about
it, or it's anyway been thrown in enough in doubt because of
the fact because of the fact that that was not the first
man that she married. So in that case, she's allowed she shouldn't
לכתחילה lechatchilah marry ראובן Reuven even in that case, but אם כנס
לא יוציא, im kanas lo yotzi, if she married ראובן Reuven in
that case, she doesn't have to get divorced. So היכי דמי, heichi
dami, what's the case? אי דאיכא עדים, ei de'ika edim, if it's
the case that there were witnesses that she had an affair with
ראובן, Reuven, so כי אתא אחר ואפסיקה לקלא, ki ata acher v'afsikah
l'kala, just because somebody came and interrupted the rumor, so מאי הוה,
mai hava, why should that make a difference? We know as a
fact she had an affair with ראובן, Reuven, we should always force
a divorce. אלא לאו, ela lav, it must be דליכא עדים, d'leika
edim, there are no witnesses, and therefore it matters did she marry
ראובן Reuven right away or only after the another guy. וטעמא דאתא
אחר ואפסיקה לקלא, v'ta'ama d'ata acher v'afsikah l'kala,
and the reason therefore that she can stay married to ראובן Reuven
is because there was this other guy in the middle
who interrupted the rumor. הא לאו הכי, ha lav hachi, if there
was not that scenario, מפקינן, mapkinan, we would make her get divorced
from ראובן, Reuven, which seems like a very good proof. It's impossible
to understand the scenario with witnesses, then we would never let her
stay married to ראובן. Reuven. It must be without witnesses, and it's
telling you, if the rumor was interrupted she can stay married to
ראובן, Reuven, if the rumor wasn't interrupted she can't stay married to
ראובן, Reuven, even though there were no witnesses to the fact of
the affair. So you see a rumor of an affair will force
a divorce if she marries the other guy, okay, not from her
husband. So the גמרא Gemara says, we'll see about her husband in
a minute. So הא לאו הכי מפקינן. ha lav hachi mafkinan. So
obviously isn't that a proof against רב Rav that you would force
a divorce from ראובן Ruvein even without witnesses? So אמר לך רב,
amar lach Rav, רב Rav will say to you, הוא הדין דאף
על גב דלא נשא אחר ואפסקה לקלא. hu hadin de'af al gav
d'lo nasa acher ve'afseke lekala. No, the same הלכה halakha would be
even if there was not a marriage in between and the rumor
was not interrupted. You're right, the scenario has to be without witnesses,
but she would not have to divorce ראובן Ruvein either way. So
אי איכא עדים מפקינן, ei ika edim mafkinan, if there are witnesses,
that's the only case we'll force a divorce. אי ליכא עדים לא
מפקינן, ei leka edim lo mafkinan, without witnesses we won't. So then
why did it speak about another guy marrying her in between if
we don't force a divorce regardless? So גמרא Gemara says והכי קאמר,
vehachi ka'amar, it says like this, דאף על גב דעשה אחר ואפסקה,
de'af al gav de'asa acher ve'afseke, even though she married another guy
in between ואפסקה לקלא ve'afseke lekala and interrupted the
rumors, לכתחילה לא יכנוס, lechatchila lo yichnos, לכתחילה lechatchila she shouldn't marry
ראובן. Ruvein. So the חידוש chiddush is not that he doesn't have
to divorce ראובן. Ruvein. She wouldn't have to divorce ראובן Ruvein even
if she married him immediately. If there are no witnesses, you're not
going to force a divorce. רב Rav is really taking a very
מקיל meikel approach here. No witnesses, you're not going to force a
divorce. The only point of the ברייתא braita said if the guy
interrupted was to be מחמיר, machmir, then even if a guy interrupted,
לכתחילה lechatchila she shouldn't marry ראובן Ruvein after the second divorce. Okay,
מיתיבי, meitivai, I'll ask you on this. במה דברים אמורים, bamei devarim
amurim, we have a ברייתא braita that says, when is this true
that you don't force a divorce from ראובן? Ruvein? כשאין לה בנים,
keshe'ein lah banim, when she didn't have children with her first husband.
אבל יש לה בנים, aval yesh lah banim, if she had children
with her first husband, לא תצא, lo tetze, she should not get
divorced, right? Because if there's children from the first husband, if you
force a divorce from ראובן, Ruvein, that is the best way to
reinforce the rumor. By forcing her to get divorced from the second
guy, why would בית דין Beit Din go to the extent of
forcing her to get divorced from the second guy unless it was
true that she was having an affair with him? So you don't
want to have to reinforce the rumor. You're concerned that they're now
עובר over because they're sleeping together and you're not allowed to continue
to sleep together if you had an affair, you know, if there
was an adulterous affair, fine. But the tradeoff is that you're making
everybody believe that the rumor was true, that's why you're forcing the
divorce, and that's not a price worth paying if there are kids
that are going to get hurt in the mix. If there are
kids that are now going to get perceived to be ממזרים. mamzerim.
So if she had, right, because if they were having an affair,
then who was the real father of these kids? Right? You don't
know who the real father of these kids is, you start suspecting
their parentage. Okay, so you will not force a divorce from ראובן
Ruvein if there are kids she had with her first husband.
ובמה דברים אמורים uvimei devarim amurim means you do force.
You do force it when there's no kids.
אה, זהו במה דברים אמורים ah, zehu bamei devarim amurim is when
do we force the divorce, which
is what the משנה Mishna says. Right. But when there is children
we don't because it'll just reinforce, because forcing a divorce reinforces the
rumor and we don't want the kids to pay the price. ואם
באו עדי טומאה, ve'im ba'u edei tumah, if there are witnesses that
they were having an affair, אפילו יש לה כמה בנים תצא. afilu
yesh lah kama banim tetze. So we don't care, so then we
can't allow her to stay married to ראובן. Ruvein. We know they
were having an affair, we know that they're אסור assur to one
another because a woman who commits adultery is forbidden to the man
she was having the affair with. We can't tolerate that. We have
objective proof she was having an affair. We force a divorce and
it's to, you know, okay, the kids, I mean they're not necessarily
ממזרים, mamzerim, maybe there'll be some suspicions raised, but nevertheless we feel
that we're not able to tolerate this union even if there are
kids in the mix. So what does that show you? It shows
you that the basic הלכה halakha was said without witnesses. Here we
think with witnesses you force a divorce even if there are kids.
Okay, without witnesses, then we said it depends. If there's no kids,
force a divorce. If there are kids, don't force a divorce. So
it shows you that even without witnesses we will force a divorce
as long as there's no kids. Right? And רב Rav says you
don't force a divorce unless there are witnesses. Here the ברייתא braita
is very clear. If there are no kids, you force the divorce
even in the absence of witnesses. Yes, David.
What's the witnesses actually observe?
Well we'll get to that. Did they actually, I mean, but they
basically observed them having sex. Like how explicitly did they see them?
I mean, you know, did they see them under the sheet? There's
a discussion in a different גמרא Gemara about the basic, I mean
the basic two possibilities is one is עד שיראו כדרך המנאפים, ad
sheyiru kederech hamena'afim, they saw them acting like people engaged in sex.
Okay, so they sort of didn't actually see the genitals, okay, but
they saw everything that made it very clear that they were actually,
it wasn't just they were outside a locked room and they heard
noises. They actually directly saw, but you know, they saw the bodies
coming together whatever without actually seeing the genitals. And the other הלכה,
halakha, again, different questions for whether it's to assume an affair and
therefore to assume that she has to get divorced from her husband
and can't marry, or then the question of let's say to actually
Michael's question about if you're actually going to try to execute somebody,
you might need even more like direct evidence. So the other
possibility is כמכחול בשפופרת, ke'michol beshifporet,
see it like the applicator in the eyelash tube. Okay, so you
can figure out that metaphor. Yes.
Are we saying force the divorce She could be getting divorced against
her will.
Well,
yes, that's the question about בית דין, Beis Din, whether when it's
a, you know, so when it says יוציא yotzi means we force
it.
Yeah, even if she would want to stay.
Sure. Sure. That's the whole חידוש chiddush about this. Okay. So the
גמרא Gemara says like this. So anyway it's clear that when there
are no kids, we're talking without witnesses and with no kids we
still force a divorce, it's a proof against רב. Rav. So the
גמרא Gemara says, all right, you're right, fine. רב מוקי לה למתניתין,
Rav moki lah lemasnisin, so רב Rav will say the משנה Mishnah
is talking about יש לה בנים ויש לה עדים. yesh lah banim
veyesh lah edim. Fine,
when רב Rav said the משנה Mishnah is that there are witnesses,
he was assuming the case that there are kids, and because there
are kids, he had to say that there were witnesses, because if
without witnesses, we wouldn't have done it since there are kids. But
basically רב Rav doesn't disagree. No kids, רב Rav would agree you
don't need witnesses. So the גמרא Gemara says, so why is רב
Rav making things complicated? So the גמרא Gemara says, ומאי דוחקיה דרב
לאוקמי למתניתין ביש לה בנים ויש לה עדים? umai dochkei deRav leokme
lemasnisin beyesh lah banim veyesh lah edim?
What forced רב Rav to assume the משנה Mishnah was talking about
kids and then he had to say, oh, then the only time
we're going to do it is when there are witnesses? דתימא דאיכא
עדים מפקינן deteima deika edim mafkinan because there are witnesses we cause
the divorce ואי ליכא עדים לא מפקינן ve-ei leka edim lo mafkinan
and if not, not. לוקמה בשאין לה בנים, lokmah beshe'ein lah banim,
why not assume the משנה Mishnah is without kids? ואף על גב
דליכא עדים, ve-af al gav deleka edim, and without kids and there
are no witnesses, simple read of the משנה, Mishnah, there's a rumor,
no kids, and you force a divorce. So אמר רבא מתניתין קשיא
ליה. amar Rava masnisin kashya leh. No, the משנה Mishnah bothered him.
מאי איריא דתני הוציאוה, mai irya detani hotzi-u-ha,
why does it say that they forced, literally it means they took
her away from her first husband? לפני הוציאה, lifne hotzi-ah,
why doesn't it just say her first husband divorced her after the
rumors? אלא, ela, so what would be the only case בית דין
Beis Din would have forced her to divorce her first husband? כוח
הוציאוה דבית דין, ko hotzi-u-ha deBeis Din, taking her away means the
court forced the first divorce, the first divorce from her husband, her
first husband. ובית דין בעדים הוא דמפקי uBeis Din be'edim hu demafki
and therefore
the only time בית דין Beis Din would have forced the divorce
from her first husband is with witnesses. So basically רב Rav is
not מחדש mechadesh anything according to הלכה, Halacha, everybody agrees. No witnesses,
you force a divorce if there are no kids. With witnesses, you
force a divorce even if there are kids. Nobody debates the fact.
רב Rav is just saying, I'm bothered by the language of the
משנה Mishnah that it sounds like they forced her to divorce her
first husband. Who is forcing a divorce from the first husband? So
must be the scenario is that there are witnesses and there are
kids, and therefore that's why they forced her to divorce, but I'm
not debating the הלכה. Halacha. הלכה Halacha would be true either way.
Okay, if there's no witnesses, then it's when the husband chooses to
divorce her. If there are witnesses, we're forced to divorce. But either
way, even without witnesses, we will force her to divorce the second
guy if she goes ahead and gets married. So that basically removes
any הלכתי halachic חידוש chidush of רב. Rav. But now what the
גמרא Gemara is going to say, and this is very important להלכה,
la-halacha, is it's going to say, no, actually רב Rav is very
serious. We will never force a divorce ever from the second guy
without witnesses. Okay, let's go look at the next at the next
line. Well, let's take a look. So, yeah, despite the rumors, without
witnesses, we will never force a divorce. Right, exactly. So the גמרא
Gemara says like, well, forcing the divorce reinforces the rumor. So the
גמרא Gemara says like this, ואי בעית אימא, ve-i-ba'is eima, if you
want to say, האי מתניתא, hai masnisa, the ברייתא Braitas that we
quoted that make it clear that you would force a divorce without
witnesses, right, if there are no kids, you force a divorce without
witnesses, that's very clear from the ברייתא. Braita. So that ברייתא Braita
is רבי היא. Rabbi-hi. That's the position of רבי, Rabbi, that, but
רב Rav disagrees. You know, either he claims that the משנה Mishnah
assumes otherwise, or רב Rav is a תנא Tanna and רב Rav
is allowed to disagree. So you're right, there's a ברייתא Braita that
says that without witnesses you would divorce as long as there's no
kids, but that's רבי, Rabbi, that's not רב. Rav. Now, how do
we know that this is a unique position of רבי? Rabbi? דתניא,
de-tanya, we taught in a ברייתא... Braita...
רוכל יוצא, rochel yotze, the spice seller, you know, we would sort
of say the merchant, we would sort of say the traveling salesman,
so husband comes home from work, and as he's coming home from
work, the traveling salesman is is leaving the house. The milkman. The
milkman's leaving the house. ואישה חוגרת בסינר, ve-ishah chogeres besinar, and his
wife is putting on her girdle. Okay, so that's pretty... I wonder
what just happened here. Okay. So, but there's no direct evidence, and
who knows? Always possible some other explanation. So אמר רבי הוא מכוער
הדבר, amar Rabbi hu mechurar hadavar, because the thing is disgusting, unseemly,
תצא, tetzei, they have to get divorced. Now, it's an interesting phrase,
הוא מכוער הדבר. hu mechurar hadavar. Does that mean that we... it
definitely... we can definitely need to assume it happened, or means like
even if we can't assume it happened, it's suspicious enough that we
don't want to sort of continue the marriage in this state of
this type of suspicious event having occurred, right? The phrase הוא מכוער
הדבר... hu mechurar hadavar... you could have used a different phrase, you
could said הוא ויש רגלים לדבר יוציא, hu ve-yesh raglayim ladavar yotzi,
right? That's a different phrase. Since there's good evidence, since there's good
basis for assuming something happened, they have to get divorced. מכוער הדבר
mechurar hadavar might be saying, I don't know if it happened or
not, but it's so unseemly that and to continue the marriage after
this type of suspicion has been raised with this type of... you
know, with this type of things that occurred that give... you know,
whether it happened or not, it's it's improper to
continue. concerns. Okay, רוק למעלה מן הקילה, Rok Lemalah Min Hakilah, let's
say there is spit on the canopy above the bed. So, I
don't exactly get, spit might be a euphemism meaning semen although רש"י
Rashi doesn't think so. Anyway, אמר רבי הן למכוער דבר תצא, Amar
Rabbi Hen L'mechuar Davar Tesei, they say it's a euphemism there. רש"י
Rashi thinks it's literal. Okay. אמר רבי הן למכוער דבר תצא. Amar
Rabbi Hen L'mechuar Davar Tesei. You know, alright, there's something pretty suspicious
going on here. It's not seemly, she has to get divorced. מנעלים
הפוכים תחת המיטה, Minalayim Hafochim Tachat Hamitah,
the shoes are upturned under the bed. What exactly that's supposed to
mean? אמר רבי הן למכוער דבר תצא. Amar Rabbi Hen L'mechuar Davar
Tesei. So, מנעלים הפוכים לחזי דמאן נינהו? Minalayim Hafochim Lechzi Deman Ninhu?
So the גמרא Gemara assumes that the shoes are overturned, meaning maybe
they're the רוכל's, Rokhel's, you know, the spice-seller's shoes. So why don't
you just look at them? They're turned over so you can't see
whose shoes they are. So just look! Look at whose shoes they
are. So the גמרא Gemara says, אלא מקום מנעלים הפוכים, Ella Mekom
Minalayim Hafochim, the place of the shoes is reversed. Again, not exactly
clear what that means. רש"י Rashi either said that there's either evidence
that somebody put their shoes under the bed and left some mark
there and turned them upside down, there aren't shoes there any now,
but it looks like somebody put their shoes under the bed. Or
that the shoes are in the wrong place, like you know where
her shoes normally are is where his shoes are, like some, something's
been happening with the,
you know, in the bedroom, that things aren't the way they should
be. What?
It's getting less and less?
Oh, that's also true. Possibly it's less and less, right.
Yeah. That's true. Yeah, yeah, yeah. That's a good point. Okay. So
anyway, what do you see? So רבי Rabbi says even if there's
not straight evidence, even if there's suspicion, תצא. Tesei. So רב Rav
says, you know what, you're right. There's a ברייתא Braita that says
if they got married even by a rumor, even without evidence, they
have to get divorced, as long as there's no kids. That's רבי.
Rabbi. I don't think that's correct. I think that the only time
you'll force a divorce is if there's direct, if there's direct evidence.
Okay. I disagree with רבי. Rabbi. And that is a big question
because nowadays, you know, this actually happens, right? You know, to cases
of adultery and affairs and suspicion and evidence. And sometimes the hardest
thing in הלכה Halacha is that you've got a suspicious husband that
actually hires a private investigator, and this happens, and they actually get,
and they get pictures.
It's great, you know, you had to go ahead and get pictures,
right? So if, the less direct evidence you have, even if there's
a lot of circumstantial evidence, רב Rav would say if there's no
עדים, Edim, you don't have to get divorced. Okay. Only if there's
עדים. Edim. Anyway, we're talking about the second guy. Presumably what's true
about the second guy is also true about the first guy, right?
The same type of evidence that you would force a divorce from
her husband she's married to now would presumably be the same amount
of evidence you would need to force a divorce or, you know,
from the second guy, although I'll mention תוספות Tosafot in a minute
about that. But let's just see how the גמרא, Gemara, the first
would presumably be the same as the second, her original husband and
the guy she's suspected of having the affair with. Let's just see
the הלכה. Halacha. I'll take the questions in a minute. גמרא Gemara
says, והלכתא כוותיה דרב,
V'hilchata Kevatei
DeRav, we rule like רב Rav that you only force a divorce
if there's witnesses. והלכתא כוותיה דרבי, V'hilchata Kevatei DeRabbi, and we rule
like רבי Rabbi that you force a divorce even with circumstantial evidence.
So the גמרא Gemara says, אה, those aren't saying the same thing.
קשיא הלכתא אהלכתא, those contradict.
לא קשיא הא בקלא דפסיק הא בקלא דלא פסיק. Lo Kashya Ha
Bekala Depasik Ha Bekala Delo Pasik. When will we force a divorce
without witnesses? It's only if it is a rumor that doesn't stop.
Okay, and that somehow, it's quite fascinating how, you know, it's אסור
Assur to tell לשון הרע, Lashon Hara, but somehow if rumors keep
on, you know, keep on, don't die, we sort of, we take
it like if there's smoke there's fire type of an attitude and
we actually think that that somewhat, you know, creates some base, basis
for believing it's true. So we're now going to talk about what
that means that the rumor doesn't die.
Does the kids, does it make a difference?
Does the kids, to this rumor? Well, kids? Oh, yes. Well, we'll
talk about that in a minute. Yeah, no. With kids you would
not do it. With kids everybody agrees you need witnesses. Okay. קלא
דלא פסיק עד כמה? Kala Delo Pasik Ad Kamma? So the גמרא
Gemara says like this, so קלא דלא פסיק וליכא עדים כרבי. Kala
Delo Pasik V'leika Edim KeRabbi. If it's a rumor that doesn't cease,
then we would force a divorce like רבי. Rabbi. Again, without kids.
קלא דפסיק, Kala Depasik, if it's a rumor that ceases, then the
only time we would force a divorce is אי איכא עדים כרב,
Ee Ika Edim KeRav, only if there are witnesses. So basically will
we force a divorce based on, without direct evidence, without witnesses? Yes,
in the case of a rumor that doesn't cease. And that's the
compromise of רב Rav and רבי. Rabbi. תוספות Tosafot points out רב
Rav and רבי Rabbi themselves wouldn't have agreed to this compromise, right?
רב Rav would say even a rumor that doesn't end, רבי Rabbi
might have said even a rumor that, even if the rumor doesn't
continue. So, but you know, that's the idea of a compromise, you
take a middle position. So the גמרא Gemara is going to פסקן
Pasken that we would, we would be concerned about it if it's
a rumor that doesn't cease. Now what does that mean? So the
גמרא Gemara says like this, וקלא דלא פסיק עד כמה? V'kala Delo
Pasik Ad Kamma? What does that mean? How long does the rumor
have to go for? So אמר אביי אמרה לי אם, Amar Abaye
Amrah Li Em, my mother said to me, which wasn't his mother,
was
his mother.
for a day and a half. My God, that is not too
long for people to be rumoring about something and for that to
constitute a קלא דלא פסיק. kolo d'lo pasik. For that to be
a pretty low standard, which is a pretty מחמיר machmir position. ולא
אמרין, V'lo amrin, now the גמרא Gemara tries to pull back a
little bit אלא דלא פסיק ביני וביני. ela d'lo pasik beinei u'beinei.
That's only if it did not, if they've been talking about it
for a day and a half without stop. אבל פסיק ביני וביני,
Aval pasik beinei u'beinei, if there's a period they stopped, the gossip
stopped talking about it, הא פסיק, ha pasik, it stopped. Now I
don't exactly know who's measuring this. What does it mean, people are
talking every single, every single second? How much of an interruption in
a day and a half? What, if I talked about it for
an hour and then I waited three hours, that's an interruption? I
don't, how many people? I don't understand this. Okay, I don't understand
how you translate this into practice.
ולא אמרין אלא דלא פסיק מחמת יירא, V'lo amrin ela d'lo pasik
machmat yira, but if they interrupt during that day and a half
and it's not considered a continuous rumor, that would only be a
legitimate interruption if it wasn't because they were afraid, like they thought
that the people they were rumoring about were going to go ahead
and do something and maybe there would be some recriminations. אבל פסיק
מחמת יירא, Aval pasik machmat yira, if there's a reason that they
would have been gossiping about it were they not afraid that there
would be some consequences, then מחמת יירא הוא. machmat yira hu. Okay,
then the interruption isn't meaningful. Again, it's so funny that we are
giving all this הלכה halakha weight to gossip. ולא אמרין אלא דליכא
אויבים. V'lo amrin ela d'leika oyvim. Now this is probably the best
way to get out of this, which is all of the idea
that a rumor creates a basis for divorce is only if the
people don't have any enemies. Okay, because then we could
say אבל איכא אויבים, aval ika oyvim, if the man or the
woman have enemies, אויבים הוא דאפקי ליה לקלא. oyvim hu d'afki leih
l'kala. So the enemies are the ones that are invested in spreading
the rumor and then you can discount it. Okay. So hopefully, maybe
there are some real צדיקים tzaddikim out there that have no enemies
in the world and for them it would be a problem. But
anyway, that certainly would be a way that a lot of people
could sort of say, you know, of course what happens if it's
not the enemies that are doing the rumoring, it's the friends that
are, sometimes your friends are your worst enemies. So anyway, okay. So,
okay, fine.
So that's what we have, that's presumably is the הלכה. halakha. So
presumably the הלכה halakha is that even on the basis of rumors,
again, if there are kids, then you're and then you're only going
to force the divorce on the second guy if there's direct evidence.
But it sounds like the conclusion here is, although we've seen some
possible outs, but strong rumors and certainly maybe some strong evidence, even
if it's not direct testimony, would be enough to force a divorce.
Is that really how it plays out למעשה? le'maaseh? So there is
a תוספות Tosafot that makes a slight little point which is huge.
Take a look at the תוספות Tosafot אמר רב הכל מודים במכוער
הדבר Amar Rav hohl Rebbe kol hamachur davar back on כ"ד עמוד
ב'. chaf dalet amud bet. He says, אמר רבינו תם כתיצא מן
הרוכל אם נשאת. Omer Rabbeinu Tam k'teitzei min harocheil im niseis. When
does רבי Rebbe say that if there's these suspicious things she has
to get divorced? That means it's enough to make her divorce from
the guy she suspected having an affair with if she wound up
marrying the milkman, then we would force a divorce based on this
evidence or based on this suspicion. Okay, דכל הסוגיא איירי בנטען. de'chol
ha'sugya airy b'nitan.
It's all about do we force a divorce from the guy who
was suspected of having the affair, not about the husband. It's about
her being stayed married to the guy she was suspected of having
an affair with. דאין לומר תצא מן הבעל. De'ein lomar tetzei min
habaal. We're not talking about getting divorced from the husband that any
of this would suffice. דאין אשה נאסרת על בעלה אלא על ידי
קינוי וסתירה. De'ein isha nis'aseret al baala ela al yedei kinui u'setira.
The only way a woman would be forced to divorce her husband
would be like it says in מסכת סוטה. Masechet Sotah. There's עדים
eidim that her husband warned her and there's עדים eidim that she
was in private with the man like it went through the סוטה
Sotah process, which is a very specific, או שיראו כדרך המנאפים. o
she'yiru k'derech hamenafim.
Or they actually saw them. They might not have had to see
the genitals, but they actually saw them having sex. Okay, so that's
the only time we would divorce a woman from her husband. So
תוספות Tosafot basically takes the גמרא Gemara that very reasonably could have
been read that as long as there's some type of reasonable suspicion
and certainly if people are gossiping about it and some type of
evidence you have to force a woman to divorce her husband. תוספות
Tosafot says no, all it's talking about if she marries the second
guy. From the husband, she's already married to him, we'll never force
a divorce unless there's direct evidence they were actually having sex.
And the kids are from the first husband or the second husband?
No, the kids case is when it's about the second guy and
that's from the first husband. But תוספות Tosafot is making the point
that we would never, although the גמרא Gemara seems, רבי's Rebbe case
seems to introduce the same type of standard vis-a-vis the husband, תוספות
Tosafot is insisting no we're just talking about the standard to apply
to the man she's suspected of having an affair with if she
goes ahead and marries him. actually force a divorce from her husband,
that would only be if there's ממש mamish direct witness, direct evidence
of seeing them having sex, not just circumstantial. One could even say,
look, I know cases that happened like this. Okay, you know that
she met up with this guy in a motel room.
Okay, alright, you didn't see them having sex, maybe they were going
to have a meeting, maybe they changed their mind in the end,
who knows what? Okay, so that takes a גמרא Gemara that would
have created a real, strong challenging like Halachic demand that would have
been very, very hard
to apply in real life and would lead to a lot of
divorces and says, no, that's all just about if she goes ahead
and marries the other guy. Okay, but in terms of her remaining
with her husband, that you need really direct evidence.
Yes, I think there's a fundamental piece that I'm missing here.
There's no עדים, edim, there's no evidence, so we do not force
her to divorce the milkman, right?
No, no, no, if there's no, if there's rumor or if there's
some type of suspicious thing, we do force her to divorce the
milkman. No, but if there's nothing, there's a rumor but it stopped
and whatever, right, then
we do not force the divorce from the milkman, right? Where's husband
number one?
Husband number one divorced her because he didn't like the rumors. And
then she went and married the milkman.
You have to assume that somewhere along the way husband number one
divorced her.
Right, but the question is if
she didn't want that divorce?
Doesn't matter, it was before רבינו גרשום. Rabbeinu Gershom.
Doesn't matter if she wanted the divorce. Okay, so that was the
little piece.
Right, right, okay, yes, I just want to make also sure, so
even though there are kids from the second guy, let's say the
first she had no kids from the first husband and there were
kids from the second husband and there are all these rumors, and
forcing the divorce may lead to more rumors. Now she has kids,
oh, forced divorce, it must be that these kids are ממזרים. mamzerim.
No, they wouldn't be ממזרים. mamzerim. Sorry? They wouldn't be ממזרים. mamzerim.
Kids that are born as a result of a man and a
woman who had an affair living together, they're over on a לאו,
lav, the kids that result are not ממזרים.
mamzerim. No, but the rumors were, oh, she had sex while she
was married with the first guy. So what? Doesn't make the kids
and now she married the milkman and had kids with him.
Yeah, doesn't mean that the kids she has with the milkman are
ממזרים. mamzerim. It's only ממזרים mamzerim that could be suspected about the
first husband. Okay, yes, רבינו גרשום Rabbeinu Gershom was the
one who said you only have one wife and
that you can't divorce your wife against her will.
Yeah, that's what I was wondering. He said that too.
Okay, so now the משנה Mishna says like this. Alright, so anyway,
huge תוספות. Tosfos. Alright, so תנן התם, Tnan hatam, back to the
גמרא. Gemara. We taught over there.
המוציא את אשתו, Hamotzi es ishto, you see, this is why you
work through all of the two brothers marrying two sisters and all
of that so you can get to today's דף. daf. Okay, so
תנן התם המוציא את אשתו משום שם רע, Tnan hatam hamotzi es
ishto mishum shem ra, if a man divorces his wife, chooses to
divorce his wife because there are suspicions of her having an affair,
that's what שם רע shem ra means, לא יחזיר. lo yachazir. He
cannot choose to remarry her after. Why? Not because of rumors as
we're going to see because of the next case. Let's read the
next case. משום נדר, Mishum neder, let's say he divorced her because
she made a vow that he felt was intolerable and he wasn't
able to live
with, and he wasn't מיפר mefer it, it was too late, and
he couldn't live with her with this vow. לא יחזיר, Lo yachazir,
he cannot remarry her. So obviously it's not about rumors here. So
what's it about with this issue of the vow? What it's about
is, it's about he'll divorce his wife because of the vow or
because there's a suspicion she had an affair, she'll go and marry
another man and then he'll say and then the woman will have
gone to some sage and got the vow annulled, you know, and
find because there's ways you can annul vows, you find a פתח
pesach and whatever, we'll learn all of מסכת נדרים. Masechet Nedarim. Or
some evidence will come to bear and the husband will say, oh,
I realize you were telling the truth, you weren't having an affair
with that guy. You know what? Had I known that you really
weren't having an affair, I never would have divorced you. Had I
known that the vow could have been annulled, I never would have
divorced you. So the fact that now you're married to another guy
and have kids, those kids are ממזרים, mamzerim, the marriage isn't good,
the divorce was always בטל, batel, right? So that's where
we're afraid he's going to say, well I only divorced assuming these
things were true. Now that I find out that they're not, the
whole divorce is בטל. batel. And we don't want her to
always and her kids to always be in danger of their status
being changed because he's going to claim, oh, I never meant it
if had I realized I wouldn't have. So what we say to
him is make sure you're divorcing her, there's going to be no
opportunity for remarriage. Halachically we're not going to let you remarry her.
So if you're divorcing her, you cannot claim it's just because I
thought the נדר, neder, it's just because I thought of this. It
has to be a deeper, more profound reason because there's no opportunity
for go-backs here. And therefore if you know that there's no opportunity
to
remarry and still the man goes ahead and divorces, then he has
no basis of saying I only did it because I thought of
the rumors, I only did it because of the נדר. neder. If
that was the only reason, you would not have done it knowing
that there was no opportunity to remarry her.
Only if she marries someone else, but let's say she doesn't marry
someone... Even if she doesn't marry someone else, even a minute, a
day later, he can't remarry her. So if you can always remarry,
you can say I only did it because I thought whatever and
I figured even if I'm wrong, we can always... always get remarried,
okay, but if you know that you can never get remarried, then
obviously we have to say that the דעת daas is much deeper
and you can't claim you wouldn't have done it had this not
happened.
What's an absolute... what's an example of a נדר neder that he
would have taken? What would he have...
no, she took a נדר. neder.
Oh, what'd she say?
I don't know, she took a נדר neder that, like, she's not
going to...
all the housework is אסור ossur on her.
You know, so he's like, I can't live with a wife who's
going to do the housework, something like that, I don't know. So,
okay. I'm sorry, that was a little sexist, but okay, it's within
the context of the גמרא. Gemara. Yes. All right, yes.
And that's how we roll?
That he can't remarry her in those cases, she
has not been involved with anybody else, you mean?
Not if the divorce... I mean, that's the הלכה. halacha. How it
plays out in practice, I don't know, like, the תשובה teshuva literature,
but the הלכה halacha is that rabbinically we don't let her remarry,
right. Okay, so it says like this. So it says, it might
be different today also with חרם דרבינו גרשום, Cherem d'Rabbeinu Gershom, the
fact that she needs to agree to it. So that might somewhat
change some of those dynamics. Once it's no longer unilateral, his ability
to claim had I known I you know I wouldn't have done
it and so on, although it still technically is unilateral, but there
is
חרם דרבינו גרשום. Cherem d'Rabbeinu Gershom. Anyway, לא פלוג. lo plug.
Meaning, like, a minute later he can't marry her? Right. So she
wouldn't have gone off and married somebody else?
Doesn't matter about marrying somebody else. We're afraid that... oh, yes, that,
yes. Fine, yes. Okay, so, okay. משום לא יחזיר. Mishum lo yachzir.
שלח ליה רבה בר הונא לרבה בר רב נחמן. Shelach lei Rabbah
bar Huna l'Rabba bar Rav Nachman. ילמדנו רבינו. Yelamdenu Rabbeinu. המגרש את
אשתו משום לעז... Hamigaresh es ishto mishum la'az... תיפח, Tipach, כנס מהו
שיוציא? kanas mahu sheyotzi? In this case, בדיעבד, bedieved, if he went
ahead and did remarry her, when he divorced her because of rumors
or divorced her because of a נדר, neder, do we let them
stay remarried? Because that's our theme, right? The whole reason we got
into all these discussions was because the משנה Mishna said by the
case of the ספק safek if you're married to רחל Rachel and
לאה, Leah, both brothers shouldn't marry, and if they married they can
stay married. And then we said if there's a rumor about an
affair with a non-Jewish woman, don't get married, if you married you
can stay married. If there's a rumor with a married woman, don't
get married and if you get married then you have to get
divorced. So the theme is כנס, kanas, if the marriage took place,
is it יוציא yotzi or לא יוציא? lo yotzi? So he's asking
that question in this case. We say you're not supposed to remarry,
man's not supposed to remarry his wife if he divorces her for
these reasons. If he did remarry her, what's the story? Does he
have to divorce her? אמר ליה תנינא, Amar lei tanina, we taught,
הנישאת על פי עד אחד... haniset al pi ed echad... no, הנטענת
על אשת איש והוציאוה מתחת ידו אף על פי שכנס יוציא. hanit'enes
al eshes ish vehotziuha mitachas yado af al pi shekanas yotzi. We
taught when the man married the woman who
was suspected of having an adulterous affair with, he בדיעבד bedieved has
to divorce her. So he thinks that's the standard rule. בדיעבד bedieved
if you're not allowed to marry then you gotta get divorced בדיעבד.
bedieved. אמר ליה מי דמי? Amar lei mi dami? How can you
compare them? התם הוציאוה. Hasam hotziuha. There it says they forced her
to divorce her husband, which at least according to רבי, Rebbi, רב
Rav meant there were witnesses that saw that she committed adultery. So
that's why we won't let her stay married to the second guy.
הכא הוציאה. Hacha hotziah.
Here he divorced her on his own. So basically the basic point
being that the reason, right, the only case of all these scenarios
where we've seen so far you force a divorce is the case
of adultery, of suspected adultery. So he says you can't make a
rule from the suspected adultery case, certainly according to רבי, Rebbi, he
says it wasn't even suspected adultery, that there were witnesses. So you
can't make a rule from that. ורבה בר רב נחמן מתניתין נמי
הוציאה תנן. V'Rabba bar Rav Nachman matnisin nami hotziah tenan. But רבה
בר רב נחמן Rabba bar Rav Nachman thinks the משנה Mishna is
not that there were witnesses, it means that the husband willingly divorced
her. And so he wants to use the case of the adultery,
of the suspected adultery as a basis to say you always have
to divorce if you weren't allowed to get married. ואכתי מי דמי?
V'akatti mi dami? But still it's not similar even if it was
only even if there weren't witnesses.
התם בעל והתם בועל. Hasam ba'al vehasam boel. There it's much more
problematic. It's the guy we think committed adultery with her. We're not
going to be so tolerant of the fact that they are now
married and living together even if it's only a rumor. They were,
you know, that's a really deeply problematic thing that they... that's a
really אסור ossur thing that they did. So the marriage now is
something that's deeply problematic. As opposed to here, it's the legitimate husband,
he divorced her, he remarried her, there's nothing ugly or wrong that
happened. They just went against the rabbinic stricture of remarrying, but there's
nothing deeply problematic. So here we should tolerate it if they get
remarried. Okay? So the גמרא Gemara says, אמר ליה שפיר דמי. Amar
lei shapir dami. No, I think it is comparable אהדדי. ahadadi. They
are comparable. הכא אמרו רבנן לא יכנוס ואם כנס יוציא. Hacha amru
rabanan lo yichnos v'im kanas yotzi. At the end of the day,
I don't worry about sociological issues, I don't worry about anything, I'm
just a technical
halachist. You say don't get married and if you get married, divorce.
הכא נמי אמרו רבנן לא יחזיר ואם כנס יוציא. Hacha nami amru
rabanan lo yachzir v'im kanas yotzi. Don't remarry and if you went
against it you have to get divorced. Of course the problem is
that most of the cases in the משנה Mishna were cases where
בדיעבד bedieved you don't have to get divorced. There's only one case,
the adultery case, which is a בדיעבד. bedieved. Anyway, the גמרא Gemara
says ולא היא. v'lo hi. So the גמרא Gemara rejects it. התם
אלומי אלמא לקלא. Hasam alumi alma l'kala. There when the... Suspected adulterer
marries this woman, he's reinforcing the rumor, right? Ah, we say, it
must be true, you know, they went and they got married afterwards.
So again that makes it intolerable, of course us then forcing them
to get divorced also reinforces this rumor, but anyway, but the act
of them getting married was more intolerable. הכא אמינא קם בה בקלה
וליתה. Hacha amina kam bei b'kala u'leisa. Here, if he divorces her
because there was a rumor and then he remarries her, it serves
the opposite purpose. It shows that the rumor must have been false.
Why else would he have remarried her? So there's other things to
factor in than just the technical question of were you over on
the דרבנן d'rabbanan or not. Again, what's also fascinating is again that
five out of the, four out of the five cases in the
משנה Mishna just now were all that בדיעבד b'diavad it's okay. There
was only one case that בדיעבד b'diavad it was not okay. Okay.
Okay, I guess we will end here.